Anita Newcomb McGee Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Anita Newcomb McGee Papers 1688-1932 (bulk 1869-1932)
MSS32110
McGee, Anita Newcomb, 1864-1940
3,000 items
12 containers plus 1 oversize
5.1 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Anthropologist and physician. Correspondence, diaries, family papers, writings, scientific and medical data, and miscellaneous material pertaining to McGee's studies of communistic societies in the United States such as the Shakers and the Bethel and Oneida communities, to her duties as acting assistant surgeon, U.S. Army in the Spanish-American War; and to the formation of the Women's Anthropological Society of America. Contains family correspondence of McGee's grandfather, Charles A. Hassler, which includes a letter from James Madison, 1832.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Davenport, Charles Benedict, 1866-1944--Correspondence.; Hassler, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1810-1846--Correspondence.; Holden, Edward S. (Edward Singleton), 1846-1914--Correspondence.; Longley, Alcander, 1832-1918--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Correspondence.; McGee family.; McGee, Anita Newcomb, 1864-1940.; Newcomb family.; Newcomb, Eric McGee, 1902-1930--Correspondence.; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909--Correspondence.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946--Correspondence.
Organizations
Bethel Community.; Oneida Community.; United States. Army--Medical care.; Women's Anthropological Society of America.
Subjects
Anthropology--Societies, etc.; Anthropology.; Collective settlements.; Communal living.; Hygiene.; Medicine.; Shakers.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Medical care.
Occupations
Anthropologists.; Physicians.
Provenance
The papers of Anita Newcomb McGee, anthropologist and physician were given to the Library of Congress by McGee between 1915 and 1950.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the papers of Simon Newcomb, Anita Newcomb McGee's father.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Anita Newcomb McGee are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1864, Nov. 4 Born, Washington, D.C.
1888 Married W. J. McGee (died 1912)
1892 Received medical degree, Columbian College, Washington, D.C.
1892 1896 Private practice, Washington, D.C.
1898 Appointed acting assistant surgeon general in charge of army under the Army Surgeon General Department Founded Society of Spanish-American War Nurses
1904 1905 Led group of volunteer nurses to Japan, establishing a field hospital for the Imperial Japanese Army and serving as military medical attaché and observer with the Japanese Army in Manchuria.
1940, Oct. 5 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Anita Newcomb McGee (1864-1932) span the years 1688-1932, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1869-1932. They consist of correspondence, drafts of articles, diaries, notebooks, scientific and medical notes, news clippings, photographs and memorabilia, with some photostatic material. The collection is organized by type of material.
An “Idea Book” contains McGee's writings on subjects such as “Happiness” and “Use of imagination in science.” A considerable amount of the correspondence is with family, especially her father, Simon Newcomb, mathematician and astronomer, and her son, Eric Newcomb McGee, who changed his name to Eric McGee Newcomb. Included are holograph copies of lectures and articles on hygiene and medical matters. There are also articles derived from McGee's studies of communist societies in the United States such as the Shakers, and the Bethel and Oneida communities. A segment of the collection relates to the formation of the Women's Anthropological Society of America, and there are letters written while McGee was acting assistant surgeon, United States Army, in the Spanish-American War.
Principal correspondents in addition to those mentioned include Gifford Pinchot, Charles Benedict Davenport, Alcander Longley, and Edward Singleton Holden.
Included in the collection is the family correspondence, 1836-1846, of McGee's grandfather, Charles A. Hassler, a surgeon in the United States Navy, containing a letter from James Madison, 1832.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material or subject.
Container List
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - A-M (Box 1)
  - N-Z (Box 2)
- Newcomb, Eric McGee, correspondence (died 1931) (Box 3)
- Diaries, 1879-1882 (Box 4)
- Family and friends correspondence (Box 4)
  - 1869-1883 (Box 4)
  - 1884-1890 (Box 5)
- Articles and notebooks (Box 6)
- Communist societies in the United States and eugenics (Box 7)
- Clippings, photographs, notes, articles (Box 7)
- Biographical sketch and notes (Box 8)
- School compositions (Box 8)
- Drawing books (Box 8)
- German literature books (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous notes and memoranda (Box 9)
- Cards and invitations (Box 10)
- Photographs (Box 10)
- Newspaper clippings (Box 10)
- Memorabilia (European trip) (Box 10)
- Business papers (Box 11)
- School reports (Box 11)
- Printed matter (Box 11)
- Hassler, Charles A., correspondence (Box 12)
- Madison, James, letter, 1832 (Box 12)
- Clayton, John, photostatic copies of letter, 1688 (Box 12)
- Accounts, 1772, 1779 (Box 12)
- Oversize album (Box OV 1)